(Aquatic noises)
(أصوات داخل البحر)
So this video was taken
هذا الفيديو تم تسجيله
at Aquarius undersea laboratory
في معمل "أكواريوس" تحت سطح البحر
four miles off the coast of Key Largo,
ببعد أربع كيلومترات عن ساحل مدينة "كي لارقو"
about 60 feet below the surface.
بعمق 60 قدم (18 متر) تحت سطح البحر
NASA uses this extreme environment
"ناسا" تستعمل هذه البيئة الصارمة
to train astronauts and aquanauts,
لتدريب رواد الفضاء ورواد البحار
and last year, they invited us along for the ride.
وفي العام الماضي قاموا بدعوتنا للذهاب معهم
All the footage was taken from our open ROV,
جميع الصور تم التقاطها بواسطة "م ت ب" المفتوح الخاص بنا
which is a robot that we built in our garage.
وهو روبوت صنعناه في ورشتنا
So ROV stands for Remote Operated Vehicle,
لذا "م ت ب" تعني "مركبة تحكم عن بعد"
which in our case means our little robot
والتي يقصد بها في حالتنا هذه أن روبوتنا الصغير
sends live video
يرسل فيديو مباشر
across that ultra-thin tether
عبر الخيط النحيف جدًّا
back to the computer topside.
إلى الحاسب الآلي بالأعلى
It's open source, meaning we publish
المركبة مفتوحة المصدر، بمعنى أننا ننشر
and share all of our design files
ونشارك جميع ملفات تصاميمنا
and all of our code online,
وجميع شفراتنا البرمجية عبر الإنترنت
allowing anyone to modify
و نسمح لأي شخص بتعديل
or improve or change the design.
أو تطوير أو تغيير التصميم.
It's built with mostly off-the-shelf parts
المركبة مصنوعة في الغالب من قطع جاهزة
and costs about 1,000 times cheaper
وكلفتها أرخص بألف مرة
than the ROVs James Cameron used
من المركبة التي استخدمها "جيمس كاميرون"
to explore the Titanic.
لاستكشاف سفينة "تايتانيك"
So ROVs aren't new.
لذلك الــ"م ت ب" ليست جديدة
They've been around for decades.
فقد تمت صناعتها منذ عقود مضت
Scientists use ROVs to explore the oceans.
وقام العلماء باستخدامها لاستكشاف المحيطات
Oil and gas companies use them for exploration
شركات النفط والغاز استخدمتها للاستكشاف
and construction.
والبناء
What we've built isn't unique.
ما صنعناه ليس فريدًا
It's how we've built it that's really unique.
ولكن كيف صنعناه هو الفريد
So I want to give you a quick story of how it got started.
لذلك أريد أن أحكي لكم قصة قصيرة عن بدايتنا
So a few years ago, my friend Eric and I
قبل عدة سنوات، صديقي "إريك" وأنا
decided we wanted to explore this underwater cave
قررنا أن نستكشف كهفًا تحت البحر
in the foothills of the Sierras.
في سفوح جبال "سييرا"
We had heard this story about lost gold
لقد سمعنا عن قصة الذهب الضائع
from a Gold Rush-era robbery, and we wanted to go up there.
في عصر الاندفاع نحو سرقة الذهب وأردنا الذهاب إلى هناك
Unfortunately, we didn't have any money
للأسف، لم يكن لدينا أي مال
and we didn't have any tools to do it.
ولم يكن لدينا أي أدوات لفعل ذلك
So Eric had an initial design idea for a robot,
وكانت لدى "إريك" فكرة مبدئية لصناعة روبوت،
but we didn't have all the parts figured out,
ولكن لم يكن لدينا فكرة عن القطع التي نحتاجها
so we did what anybody would do in our situation:
لذلك قمنا بما يمكن أن يقوم به أي شخص بوضعنا
we asked the Internet for help.
قمنا بطلب المساعدة عبر الإنترنت
More specifically, we created this website,
وبشكل دقيق، قمنا بإنشاء هذا الموقع
openROV.com, and shared our intentions and our plans
openROV.com وقمنا بمشاركة أهدافنا وخططنا
For the first few months, it was just Eric and I
خلال أشهر قليلة، فقط إريك وأنا
talking back to each other on the forums,
من كان يتحدث عبر المنتديات
but pretty soon, we started to get feedback
ولكن بعدها بوقت قصير، بدأنا بتلقي ردود وآراء
from makers and hobbyists,
من مصنعين وهواة
and then actually professional ocean engineers
ثم من مهندسي محيطات محترفين
who had some suggestions for what we should do.
والذين كانت لديهم اقتراحات لما يفترض بنا عمله.
We kept working on it. We learned a lot.
ظللنا نعمل على هذا. تعلمنا كثيرًا
We kept prototyping, and eventually,
واصلنا صناعة نماذج للمركبة، وأخيرًا،
we decided we wanted to go to the cave. We were ready.
قررنا الذهاب للكهف. فقد كنا مستعدين.
So about that time, our little expedition became quite a story,
وأثناء ذلك الوقت، ما أنجزناه أصبح قصة،
and it got picked up in The New York Times.
وقامت بتغطيتها جريدة "نيويورك تايمز".
And we were pretty much just overwhelmed
وكنا مغمورين نوعًا ما
with interest from people who wanted a kit
باهتمام الناس الذين أرادوا القطع
that they could build this open ROV themselves.
ليقوموا بأنفسهم بتجميع المركبة
So we decided to put the project on Kickstarter,
لذلك قررنا وضع المشروع في موقع "KickStarter"
and when we did,
وعندما قمنا بذلك،
we raised our funding goal in about two hours,
حصلنا على التمويل الذي نحتاجه خلال ساعتين
and all of a sudden, had this money to make these kits.
وفجأة، صار لدينا المال الكافي لعمل القطع المطلوبة
But then we had to learn how to make them.
ولكن اضطررنا لتعلم كيفية عملها.
I mean, we had to learn small batch manufacturing.
أقصد، اضطررنا لتعلم كيفية الصناعة بكميات قليلة
So we quickly learned that our garage
وخلال لحظات، أدركنا أن ورشتنا
was not big enough to hold our growing operation.
لم تكن كبيرة بما فيه الكفاية لاحتواء صناعة القطع
But we were able to do it, we got all the kits made,
ولكن استطعنا إنجازها، فقد قمنا بصناعة جميع القطع
thanks a lot to TechShop, which was a big help to us,
شكرًا جزيلًا لورشة "TechShop" الذين ساعدونا بشكل كبير
and we shipped these kits all over the world
وقمنا بشحن القطع لأنحاء العالم
just before Christmas of last year,
مباشرة قبل الكريسماس في السنة الماضية
so it was just a few months ago.
والذي كان قبل أشهر قليلة ماضية
But we're already starting to get video
وبدأنا حاليًّا بالحصول على فيديوهات
and photos back from all over the world,
وصور من جميع أنحاء العالم
including this shot from under the ice in Antarctica.
من ضمنها هذه اللقطة من تحت الثلج في الأنتاركتيكا
We've also learned the penguins love robots.
وأيضًا أدركنا أن البطاريق تحب الروبوتات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we're still publishing all the designs online,
وحاليًّا لا زلنا ننشر جميع تصاميمنا عبر الإنترنت،
encouraging anyone to build these themselves.
لنحفز أي شخص ليصنعها بنفسه.
That's the only way that we could have done this.
وهذه الطريقة الوحيدة التي مكنتنا من إنجاز ذلك.
By being open source, we've created
بما أننا مصدر مفتوح، فقد قمنا بإنشاء
this distributed R&amp;D network,
شبكة الأبحاث والتطوير هذه،
and we're moving faster than any venture-backed counterpart.
ونحن نتطور أسرع من أي تجارة أخرى مماثلة
But the actual robot is really only half the story.
ولكن الروبوت كان فقط نصف القصة.
The real potential, the long term potential,
الإمكانيات الحقيقية، الإمكانيات طويلة المدى،
is with this community of DIY ocean explorers
هي بوجود مستكشفي المحيطات "الذين يصنعون بأنفسهم"
that are forming all over the globe.
الموجودين في مختلف أنحاء العالم
What can we discover
ما الذي يمكن أن نستكشف
when there's thousands of these devices
عندما تكون هناك مئات الآلاف من هذه المنتجات
roaming the seas?
تجول في البحار؟
So you're probably all wondering: the cave.
أظنكم جميعًا تتساءلون: الكهف.
Did you find the gold?
هل وجدتم الذهب؟
Well, we didn't find any gold,
حسنًا، لم نجد أي ذهب.
but we decided that what we found was much more valuable.
ولكنا أدركنا أن ما وجدنا كان أكثر قيمة بكثير.
It was the glimpse into a potential future
كانت اللمحة الخاطفة لمستقبل محتمل
for ocean exploration.
لاستكشاف المحيطات.
It's something that's not limited to the James Camerons of the world,
إنها شيء غير محصور على "جيمس كاميرون" (المستكشفين) حول العالم
but something that we're all participating in.
ولكنه شيء نشارك فيه جميعًا
It's an underwater world
إنه عالم ما تحت المياه
we're all exploring together.
نستكشفه جميعًا مع بعضنا.
Thank you.
شكرًا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)